<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Reverend Father in God, John, Lord Bishop of Bristol, at his primary visitation in Bristol, October 30 and now publish'd at His Lordships request, as also the desire of several others that heard it / by John Gaskarth ...</title>
            <author>Gaskarth, John, d. 1732.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42431</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G288</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18419</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12871262</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12871262</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94795</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42431)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94795)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 380:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Reverend Father in God, John, Lord Bishop of Bristol, at his primary visitation in Bristol, October 30 and now publish'd at His Lordships request, as also the desire of several others that heard it / by John Gaskarth ...</title>
                  <author>Gaskarth, John, d. 1732.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XI, 24 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Visitation sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94795:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the Right Reverend Father in God, JOHN, Lord Biſhop of BRISTOL, At His <hi>Primary Viſitation</hi> IN BRISTOL, <hi>October</hi> 30. And now Publiſh'd at his Lordſhips Requeſt; as alſo the deſire of ſeveral others that heard it. By <hi>John Gaskarth,</hi> Fellow of <hi>Pembroke-Hall</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and Vicar of St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> in <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, MDCLXXXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:94795:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>A <hi>Sermon Preached upon the firſt occaſion after the Death of His Grace,</hi> John <hi>Duke of</hi> Lauderdale, <hi>in the Chappel at</hi> Ham; <hi>by</hi> John Gaskarth, <hi>his late Graces Chaplain, and Fellow of</hi> Pembroke-Hall <hi>in</hi> Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:94795:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Reverend Father in God, JOHN Lord Biſhop of BRISTOL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS in Obedience to Your Lordſhip, I make theſe Publick, ſo in purſuance of the ſame Duty to my Eccleſiaſtical Superior, and as the wiſeſt thing I can do, our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty being always our greateſt Wiſdom, I put them under Your Lordſhips Protection, who not only from Your Epiſcopal Learning, and Piety, are moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly qualified to be a Patron in this kind; but from Your Paternal care of the Author himſelf, and <hi>theſe Studies and Endeavours</hi> of his,
<pb facs="tcp:94795:3"/>which You have brought into the World, are obliged to be ſo: As for <hi>them,</hi> I can ſay no more, but that they are extreamly Honeſt, and have the Charitable deſign of Preaching in them. And that they may have a due influence upon Your Lordſhips Subordinate Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus, to make us all Good Men, and effectual Preachers of the Goſpel; as alſo, to reduce thoſe that have forſaken the aſſembling of themſelves together in the Charity of Chriſts Flock, and eſtabliſh <hi>Unity</hi> among us, and Your Lordſhip, the common Father of <hi>it,</hi> which is the greateſt Bleſſing that I can requeſt for us, for them, and for your Lordſhip, is the earneſt Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips, Moſt Obedient Son, and Humble Servant,</hi> John Gaskarth.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94795:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts XI. 24.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For he was a good man, and full of the holy Ghoſt, and of Faith, and much people were added unto the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Shall not give any Hiſtorical account of the Text, either as it relateth to the Subject of it, the Holy Apoſtle <hi>Barnabas,</hi> how he was a Good Man, and full of the holy Ghoſt, and of Faith; or as it reſpects the People Converted by him, what Multitudes they were; but ſhall only inſiſt upon the connexion of theſe two Propoſitions, becauſe <hi>he was a good man,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>much people were added unto the Lord.</hi> From whence I ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the neceſſity that thoſe of the Prieſtly Function are under of being good, in order to the happy ſucceſs of their Miniſtry. And this I ſhall endeavour upon theſe Arguments from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that he who is otherwiſe an ill Man in any Inſtance,</p>
            <p>Firſt, He cannot be Univerſal in his Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Nor, Secondly, Sound in his Principles.</p>
            <p>Nor, Thirdly, Perſuaſive and prevalent upon his hearers.</p>
            <p>Nor, Fourthly, Can he ſpeak with ſufficient boldneſs.</p>
            <p>Nor, Fifthly, With any Authority.</p>
            <p>Nor, Sixthly, Can he be induſtrious enough in his high Calling.</p>
            <p>And, Seventhly, If he could be all this, his ill Example will hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the good Effect of his Preaching.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, A Bad Man cannot be univerſal in his Doctrine, he that would be a true Preacher of Righteouſneſs, and have the proper efficacy and ſucceſs of it, muſt deal impartially with ſin, and level his Diſcourſes at every particular of it; he muſt reprove all Impiety whatſoever, and not ſuffer the leaſt ſin without its juſt cenſure and reprehenſion. But he that is perſonally guilty of any open Vices, will be apt to repreſent them too favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94795:4"/>and not in their own proper and ugly Colours, rather of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering what may be probably ſpoken for their Apology or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, than give a juſt Deſcription of their abominable Nature, and of thoſe bitter Conſequences that do attend the commiſſion and habit of them. For every touch of his Pencil upon thoſe Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will open a freſh Wound in his own Boſom, and torment him with the diſmal apprehenſions of his own Guilt, and the eternal Miſery belonging to it; this will rouſe up his benummed Spirit, and hinder all his quiet ſatisfaction in his former Vices. For ſuch a monſtrous thing is ſin, that as long as we have any due reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in us, or until we have debauched our judging Faculties, and be arrived to a Spiritual Lethargy, and ſenſleſs ſtate of Mind through the cuſtom of it, there is no pleaſure to be found in it. This Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon thoſe Vices that he himſelf is guilty of, will ſcare his Soul with thoſe neceſſary terrors of a ſinful Courſe, and repreſent to him the lamentable Circumſtance that he is in; this will rub up his benummed Spirits into a lively Senſation of thoſe putrifying Sores that his ſins have left in him, and ſo bring him to that painful thing of remorſe for them, and an awakened apprehenſion of the juſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert and puniſhment of them; and all this being no Bodily mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but in the mind it ſelf, that Seat and Centre of perception, muſt needs be ſharp and inſupportable, according to that of the Wiſe Man (<hi>Prov.</hi> 18.14.) <hi>A wounded Spirit who can bear;</hi> and therefore we may well ſuppoſe that this obnoxious Perſon will paſs by his own Offences, or not commemorate them with that juſt aggravation that belongs to them, ſeeing there is ſelf-Condemnation in it, and he aſſigns himſelf over to all the Miſeries of another World in that very Inſtance. So that he who lives in the Practice or Habit of any Vice, is likely to be but a lame Doctor; and cannot <hi>univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally reprehend ſin, which</hi> nevertheleſs is abſolutely neceſſary to a right promotion of the Chriſtian Holineſs, according to the true ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and comprehenſion of it, in his hearers, ſince St. <hi>James</hi> hath told us (2.10.) <hi>that whoſoever ſhall keep the whole Law, and yet of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend in one point, he is guilty of all.</hi> There is an Univerſal Obedience due to Gods Precepts, and therefore he that offends againſt one, does offer the ſame Contempt and Indignity to the All-wiſe Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94795:4"/>giver; as he that tranſgreſſeth more largely; he is guilty of the Breach of that Obedience, and conſequently puniſhable as well as if he had broken all. So that he who remains in the Cuſtom, or under the Dominion of any ſin himſelf, muſt needs prove but a very inef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Prieſt, and Miniſter of the Goſpel, he only preaching in this confinement, and not generally to all, can never promote the work of Converſion in that extent he ought to do, or advance a common Salvation to all Men, according to the Comprehenſion of thoſe Merits which were the Purchaſe of it; nay, 'twere well if he were only ineffectual, but, alas! by ſpeaking too favourably of his own Vices, as he muſt needs do, <hi>unleſs</hi> we ſhould ſuppoſe an extraordinary Impulſe or Violence upon him, which perhaps ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times is, by Propheſying ſmooth and pleaſant things, ſuch as are more ſuitable to depraved Nature, he is likely to have a greater influence upon the People, and immerſe them deeper in their own Ruine. For this is the fundamental Miſery of Man, that he ſubmits himſelf too much to his carnal Affections, by this means advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to an undue ſtrength in him, and then too greedily em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces whatſoever can be contrived to defend and patroniſe his Vices, which are only the purſuits or gratifications of theſe Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, thus <hi>Jerem.</hi> (5.31.) <hi>The Prophets propheſie falſly, and my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple love to have it ſo.</hi> This was the Caſe of backſliding <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and doubtleſs is ſtill with the generality of Men, he ſhall have the moſt Proſelytes that gives the greateſt liberty to corrupt Nature, and moſt indulges the evil Inclinations of it; as may be exemplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the flouriſhing eſtate of our Neighbour-Church, which, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! is too much Catholick, although in many things it be not Chriſtian. But we may ask the Queſtion, with the Prophet, And what ſhall be done in the end thereof? It muſt needs be a terrible end that muſt befall theſe Men, who have thus miſled whole Multitudes into Ruine, through their Deluſions and falſe Doctrines.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A vitious Perſon cannot be ſound and Orthodox in his Doctrine: It is abſolutely neceſſary, in order to give a true Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in any thing, that the proper Faculty in that Caſe be in a right Frame and Diſpoſition, otherwiſe the thing will not appear in its own Natural Qualifications, but be repreſented in a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94795:5"/>manner, according to the Diſtemper of the Faculty. Thus to men under ſome Diſeaſes of Body, all Objects do appear in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due Colours, Figure, and Magnitude, perfectly other things than they are in their own Nature. So that if the Mind of man be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed and out of order, that being the Faculty by which he judges of Divine Things, he can have no juſt perception of them. But Vices and Immorality do quite debauch all our Faculties, they blind them with Paſſions, and warp them with undue Affections, and pervert all their Senſe and Knowledge of Spiritual Objects; what Ruines theſe have brought into our Nature is too apparent from the fall; how dusky are our Underſtandings at the beſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince, unleſs they be advanced above themſelves through Grace, and have a Beam of the Divine Wiſdom diſplayed upon them? How falſe in their Judgments, and how apt, in a baſe Inclination to Senſe, to prefer the Worſe before the Better, Earth before Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the Empty and Fading Enjoyments here, before the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial and Permanent Poſſeſſions of another World? How ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure then muſt thoſe Minds be, and how incapable of diſcerning Spiritual things, that beſides the injury done to us, or the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parement of our Original Conſtitution in the ſin of our firſt Parents, are further depraved with cuſtomary Vices, and live under the influence and habit of them? Such diſtorted Minds as theſe can no more perceive or reliſh the Noble Excellencies of Vertue, than blind men can apprehend the Beauty of Colours, or thoſe that are deaf the Harmony of Muſick, they both wanting their proper Faculties in their ſeveral Caſes. There is a refined ſenſation, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Platinus</hi> ſpeaks, which is only obtained from vertuous living, abſolutely neceſſary for our apprehenſion of Diviner things, and therefore <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> frequently intimates in his Morals, that 'tis impoſſible for any to have a right Senſe and Notion of Vertue, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they be alſo good, and have lived under the Influence of it.</p>
            <p>Thus he that is a Wine-bibber, and places his whole delight in the ſilly brisk impertinences of that Liquor, will not be able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern the true pleaſure and ſatisfaction which is in Temperance; nay, he will rather argue in the defence, and for the neceſſity of his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94795:5"/>Vice; that man is in his own nature too grave and ſerious a thing, and his Life is but a melancholly buſineſs at the beſt, unleſs you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe into him ſome quicker and more aiery Spirits than his own; when, alas, the Effect of this is freely to inflict that upon himſelf, which, if received from another, might well be accounted the greateſt Injury; that is, for the time perfect, Madneſs and Diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and 'tis Gods great mercy that he does not in juſtice puniſh this great abuſe of Underſtanding, or his beſt Talent committed to Men, and make that madneſs perpetual, extending it ſelf through his whole Life. But bleſſed be his Holy Name, that gracious Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing takes better care of us, than either to reward or puniſh us ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our deſervings.</p>
            <p>And he that is inſlaved to that ſordid thing of Covetouſneſs, or has his mind determined to the Poſſeſſions of this World, will ſcarcely be perſwaded of the Vertue of Beneficence, and being Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable. He will be more apt to conclude after this manner, that God may make our Heaven Braſs, and our Earth Iron, and hinder all our Proviſion and Increaſe at home; he may incompaſs us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with foreign Enemies, and ſtop the income of our Riches from abroad, and he may make theſe ſad circumſtances of things to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue for a long ſeaſon; what then will become of me, when through my Charity and the ſcarceneſs of the Land, there is nothing left in my hands? Is it not better to reſerve my Riches, and provide of my own Store for the evil time, than expoſe my ſelf to theſe Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties? This is his depraved opinion of things, and his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice from it; and indeed 'tis very true, God may of his infinite Mercy ſend theſe Judgments upon a ſinful Nation, for their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and Amendment; but he might conſider, if he had freedom for it, what folly it is to rebell againſt God, who has commanded the Rich to ſupport the Poor, that their abundance ſhould be a ſupply for the others wants, when in this neglect of his, or this carnal Wiſdom to ſecure himſelf, he provokes God to deprive and denude him of all that he has, which he is ſo retentive of, becauſe he does not pay the juſt homage of it; I ſay he might conſider this, what folly it is to rebel againſt an expreſs Precept, which alſo has this preſent conſequence of it, and diſtruſt that careful Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94795:6"/>that clothes the Lilies of the Field, and feeds the young Ravens that call upon him. Shall That neglect Man the Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work-man-ſhip of Heaven, for whoſe enjoyment this lower World was created; ſhall That neglect man, in the very performance of his Duty? <hi>O ye of little Faith.</hi> It is a free thought that of <hi>Solomon,</hi> which the captivated Soul of a covetous Perſon is not capable of, that Charity is our ſureſt Proviſion, as engaging God for us, (<hi>Eccl.</hi> 11.1, 2.) <hi>Caſt thy bread upon the waters, and thou ſhalt find it after many days. Give a portion to ſeven, and alſo to eight, for thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not what evil ſhall be upon the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus alſo the proud Perſon, who is only filled with emptineſs, (if I may ſo ſpeak) or the vain opinion of himſelf, will not be able to obſerve the great Vertue of Humility, he will rather account it a very debaſement of himſelf in ſeveral inſtances of it; than as it really is the moſt becoming and graceful Ornament of a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or indeed a neceſſary thing to dependent Beings, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will more inſiſt upon thoſe Excellencies that Mans Nature is inveſted with, and upon theſe thoughts advance himſelf higher in his own folly; alas! not conſidering that none of theſe Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives which Man enjoys, were originally his own, but only through Gods goodneſs are derived to him from that infinite Ocean of the Divine Nature, and therefore there is no reaſon for our glorying, or Self-eſteem, ſuppoſing we ſtill maintained our firſt ground, and poſſeſſed the perfections of our Creation; but the greateſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a profound Humility in all of us, is the ſenſe of our free deſcent from theſe, that we have violated our indiſpenſable obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to our Maker, in our repeated Sins and Rebellions againſt him, and thereby have depraved our Natures, and contracted ſo many Infirmities into them.</p>
            <p>The envious Man, in like manner, will be apt to Apologiſe for his worſt of Vices, affirming that a like portion of things does be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to <hi>all men,</hi> being equal by Nature, <hi>who</hi> have the ſame attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in them, or <hi>who</hi> are of the ſame growth, and ſtanding in Vertue; and he ſees no reaſon to ſuſpect his own proficiency, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his Diſcontentment, and his Envy from it, be a ſufficient proof againſt him. But in this poſſeſſion of his he cannot duly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94795:6"/>which would quite deliver him from his Envy, that God diſcerns the moſt hidden Diſpoſitions and Tempers of Men, with their Differences to one another, and thereforek nows beſt how to diſpenſe theſe outward enjoyments to every ones particular benefit; and he affords him this ſcant proportion to prevent Intemperance, or Covetouſneſs, or ſome other Vices in him, which although he perceives not, who only underſtands himſelf from his opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, either of Sin or Vertue, yet perhaps he is naturally propenſe and inclined to.</p>
            <p>And the Luxurious and Wanton Perſon, cannot perceive the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly nature of Chaſtity, and the ſtrict Obligation he has to it, he will rather defend his polluted Practices from the agreement of his Vice, that his very Principles and Conſtitution prompts him to it, and 'tis certainly lawful to enjoy the proper ſatisfactions of our Nature, or elſe the Wiſdom of our Maker might be called in Queſtion, and his Goodneſs towards us. And it is very true, we may ſo; but we muſt conſider, which Men in this hurry of Vice cannot do, that God has made us better than Brute Creatures, and given us Faculties above them, which we ought to obtain our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſatisfactions from; or at leaſt when we taſte of the Animal Nature, in a due Meaſure and Regulation by them. Thus it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that Covetouſneſs, and Pride, and Envy, and Wantoneſs, brings a certain Infirmity into our Reaſons, and depraves our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in their reſpective Caſes; and I might Demonſtrate that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular Vice, indulged and adhered to, does produce ſome Error or other in Point of Doctrine; and although every Vicious Perſon either has not ſufficient Parts, and Ingenuity, to found a new Hereſie; or has not arrived at ſuch a Degree of Impudence to go againſt the Sound Doctrines and Venerable Authority of the whole Church, yet he is certainly Heterodox in ſome Opinion or other. Immorality, without queſtion, is the great Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of falſe Divinity, all theſe Peſtulent Hereſies that have rent the Seamleſs Coat, and Church of Chriſt, for above theſe ſixteen hundred years, have ariſen from this Original. What was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that the Arch-Heretick <hi>Simon,</hi> ſhould defend all Vices lawful, but that he himſelf was. Univerſally addicted to them? I paſs by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94795:7"/>that wild Aſſertion of his, that he was the only Deity, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſeveral names of the Bleſſed Trinity, at different times had appeared to Mankind, which yet was the plain Product of his Pride, as is evident from his Conference with the Apoſtles (<hi>Acts</hi> 8.19.) when he would have bought the Holy Ghoſt of them, that is, the glaring Gift of working Miracles; I ſay, I paſs by this, as being a meer Deluſion of his upon the People, which from the Senſe of Humane Infirmities, he could never perſwade him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of. Why did thoſe filthy Dreamers, the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> deſpiſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and ſpeak Evil of Dignities, ſo highly maintain the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty, as thereby to exempt all Chriſtians from the juſt Authority of King, or Maſter? Why did they ſo contumeliouſly treat the Apoſtles, and Governours of the Church, denying all their Superiority over them; but becauſe of thoſe two horrible Vices which they were infected with? Firſt, according to St. <hi>Peter's</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, that they walked after the Fleſh, in the Luſt of unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, allowing themſelves in the full enjoyments of their Carnal Affections: and therefore no wonder, if they hated all thoſe who offered any reſtraint to them; if the very Apoſtles, who exhorted all Men to the inward Purity of the Goſpel, not only to abſtain from Sinful Actions, but endeavour after an undefiled Spirit and Heart within them, if they were deſpiſed and rejected by them: Or, Secondly, becauſe of their Pride and Inſolency, which they had learned from their Maſter the Magician, not enduring to ſee others have a pre-eminency, and be Lords over them. And I am confident that this baſe Vice, this Spirit of Pride, is the true cauſe why our Brethren <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> at home, do recede from the Church, that ſpecial Place of Grace, and Bleſſing; and deſpiſe their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Governours. Pride, I ſay, is moſt likely the Principal cauſe of their Separation, in that they ſo contemn the lawful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; although perhaps in an obſtinate adherence to this Vice, they may afterwards be blinded with it, and fall into an Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conſcience from it. Why alſo did theſe ſame <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> deny the reality of Chriſts comeing in the Fleſh, but becauſe they would not live a Goſpel Life, or obſerve the Holineſs of his Doctrine? And why did they affirm it lawful to deny Chriſt in time of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94795:7"/>but becauſe they had ſoftned their Spirits, and loſt the invincible Chriſtian Courage, in a brute purſuance of their Luſts and Carnal living? For we read of the Primitive Martyrs, that they often abſtained from their lawful enjoyments, and uſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to great ſeverities, as a due preparation for that Fiery Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. What is the reaſon that even in our own Age, in all the Light of the Goſpel, ſome have been ſo bold to deny the Exiſtence of their Maker, when the inſtances of himſelf, or a wiſe Providence, are ſo apparent in the World, when we can give no account of any particular in Nature, without recurring to a Deity, or an Infinite Power and Wiſdom, that was the Cauſe of it; and when this gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Being is the greateſt ſupport and comfort of our Lives in all our Circumſtances whatſoever: One would not deſire to live in a World void of Providence, ſaid the Heathen Emperour; nay, 'twould be the moſt inſupportable miſery to do ſo: And why alſo do men ſo induſtriouſly annihilate themſelves, and deny the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of their own Souls, but becauſe they have led ſuch pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted lives as cannot endure ſuch a righteous Being, or that which is neceſſary to it, an after Judgment. Thus we ſind (and might be more particular, if 'twere needful) that every vicious man is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound and erroneous in ſome of his Opinions. This is the proper Efficacy of any Sin, when we come to the Habit and Cuſtom of it, that it changes our natural Conceptions of things, and inclines, and reconciles our Judgments towards it; and therefore how much (think we) does it concern the Miniſters of the Goſpel, thoſe that watch over the Souls of the People, and muſt give an account to God for them, to endeavour after an univerſal Holineſs of Life and Converſation, leſt by living under the influence of any Vice, their Doctrines be corrupted and falſe, tending rather to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of their Hearers, than the building them up in their moſt Holy Faith; and if ſo, they ruine not only the People, but more eſpecially, and in a more grievous manner themſelves alſo, who have been the cauſe of it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, A vicious man cannot be ſo perſwaſive and prevalent upon his Hearers; it is not to ſpeak with great fluency of words, or in a loſty ſtile, or to entertain his Auditors with round and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94795:8"/>delectable Rhetorick, that will perſwade Men, and procure their Aſſent in any matter; all this in an ill deſign, when the Cheat is once diſcovered, and the intent of impoſing upon them fairly laid open, will exaſperate the more, and ſet their conſent at a greater diſtance; they'll then begin to ſuſpect all that ſuch a Perſon ſays to them, and if he offers any juſt, or equitable matter, that muſt be aſcribed to the power of his Eloquence, which can change the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Colours of things, and repreſent them as he pleaſes; rather than to <hi>truth it ſelf,</hi> and ſo be rejected for the ſake of <hi>that:</hi> Thus his Rhetorick will create a prejudice againſt him; and the more Eloquent he is, the more ſuſpicious they will be of him, and the more he'll be diſtruſted by them. Nor is it always ſound Truths and clear Argument that will certainly find approbation; one may reaſon of Righteouſneſs, Temperance, and Judgment to come, as concerning Truths as ever were inſiſted upon, and yet not gain many Proſelytes; indeed this laſt terrible Topick of Judgment to come, may well make Men tremble, as it once did <hi>Felix;</hi> but this motion is not like to continue long, when they ſhall obſerve, that the Author of this great Doctrine does not live as if ever he expected the event of it; when they take notice that his actions are not influenced by that ultimate end; that he is neither ſo Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate nor Righteous, as he ought to be who believes that he ſhall come to an impartial Tribunal, and juſt Sentence in another world; they'll preſently ſuſpect his whole reaſoning; and although they can diſcern no Fallacy in it, yet they will conclude, that there is doubtleſs ſome there, or elſe, ſay they, why does not he himſelf direct his Converſation accordingly, who is as much concerned in the buſineſs as we; this is ſome counterfeit affrightment or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to bring us to ſome advantage of his, but he ſhall not have his deſign upon us; his Practice is a better demonſtration to us than all his Words and Diſcourſes are. So that even Truth it ſelf, when ſpoken by all kind of Perſons, will not prevail in the World: If a bad Man ſhould appear in a Patronage of Vertue, let his Arguments be never ſo cogent, yet his Vices, or Immoral living will betray the Cauſe. This is the ſad conſequence of open Sin in thoſe, whoſe Office is to inſtruct others. Nor is it vehement Aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verations,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94795:8"/>or ſtrength of Oaths, that can always obtain an aſſent to them, one does not commence a credible Author from theſe; for he that is wicked in other reſpects, why ſhould we ſuppoſe that he'll ſcruple to aſſert a Lye, and give the confirmation of Perjury to it, when that will ſerve his purpoſe. Some Men may fill their Mouths with big Oaths and Imprecations, even till they burſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, in the words of St. <hi>Chryſoſt. (tom.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 514.) and never be the more credited for that; others, ſays he, only nodding with the Head, will gain a Deference and Belief to them; and therefore this is that effectual <hi>Orator</hi> that irreſiſtably perſwades and forces Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent whereſoever <hi>it</hi> appears; <hi>namely, An uprightneſs of Life, and a juſt Converſation towards all Men.</hi> What as does proceed and flow from theſe, can never want Approbation, good Counſel, and ſober Inſtructions, when a ſincere and honeſt Heart does dictate them, muſt needs be embraced by all Men: There can be no ground of Objection to them, nor any Suſpicion to prevent them, when the Probity of the Counſellor and his Vertue is once diſcovered. For as a Good Man is the like lieſt to have the beſt knowledge of things, his mind being in the moſt fit and proper frame for that purpoſe, ſo he will repreſent nothing to any Perſon, as the matter of his Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but what he is fully convinced of to be true himſelf, and ſo from his known Honeſty he is preſently conſented to by all Men.</p>
            <p>And moreover he has this great advantage, that the Image of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue being fairly deſcribed upon his mind, he has the true Zeal of it, or a certain impulſe within him, for its due promotion in the World. So that when he does exhort to the atchievement of any laudable thing, he has that very movement of Spirit, and lively concern within himſelf, which he would imprint in the minds of his Hearers; when he does incite to the love of <hi>God, that moſt infinitely gracious Being, who</hi> has prevented us with ſo many Bleſſings, you may ſee the vehement Pulſes and Elevations of his own Heart, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his very Soul fluttering up towards that great Object. When he perſwades to any Vertue, with what Alacrity does he perform it? How lively does he expreſs his own Complacency in that, while he is preparing the Conſent of his Hearers? When he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94795:9"/>from any Vice, what Horror and Deteſtation may you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in him, and how plainly may one diſcern his Soul againſt it? And ſeeing there is ſuch a general Sympathy in the Nature of Men, that they naturally follow one anothers motions, when in the uſe of his Rhetorick he recommends Vertue, or when he declares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Vice, and in that very thing expreſſes the different Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his own Mind; his Love of the one, and his Averſion to the other; how muſt he carry the Souls of the People along with him? And therefore it is the Good Man that is the moſt prevailing Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who leaves no Power to refuſe to him, but forces his Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions upon the Minds of his Hearers, and irreſiſtably works an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in them. And if there ſhould be none of this excitement of Affections, yet there is a proper Air or Spirit in honeſt Language, plainly diſcovering a Vertuous Man, which hath a ſtrange Preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and Conviction with it. All which the two Great Orators, <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Tully,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gorgias p.</hi> 326. <hi>Ed. Baſ.</hi>
               </note> knew very well, the one laying down this Apophthegm, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: And the other this, <hi>Oratorem fieri vitae dignitate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be Objected, And cannot a bad Man counterfeit all this? Cannot he rouſe up his Paſſions, and appear as concerned for Vertue, and as eager againſt Vice, as he that has that true ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of Mind and Affections in him? To which I anſwer, No; let him uſe all the Artifices immaginable, and perſonate his part with never ſo much Caution; yet a diſcerning Eye will quickly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him to be no other than an Impoſter. His diſſembled Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes will certainly want ſome of thoſe Characters which are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways obſervable in true ones, they will be either ſuch extravagant things, as to the matter of them, as will plainly declare his ſmall Skill and Acquaintance with Goodneſs; or elſe be ſpoken ſo remiſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without the reliſh of mind, and thoſe raiſed Affections, which conſtantly poſſeſs Good Men, when they are imployed upon the Theme of Vertue; that the Fallacy will be evident: and although perhaps he may be ſuch a fanciful Mimick, as to act ſome of theſe indiſſerently well; yet he will certainly err in ſome particular or other, as to the Meaſure, Order, or Decorum of it; he will ſo
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94795:9"/>falſly accent his Paſſions, placing the grave and lene in undue cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, that it muſt be manifeſt that he acts not his own part, but (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) buſies himſelf in other mens matters, and may challenge a Title to that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Why doſt thou preach my law, whereas thou hateſt to be reformed.</hi> Hypocriſie is no ſuch eaſie buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and although it be much endeavoured, and bunglingly done by many, yet 'tis ſeldom ſo happily performed, but an indifferent diſcretion may perceive it. Let a Man of this deſign uſe all the Art and Diligence poſſible, yet an unnatural repreſentation, or ſome uncouth thing or other will declare him not the Perſon that he would appear to be. <hi>Prodit enim ſe quamlibet cuſtodiatur, ſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio, nec unquam tanta fuerit eloquendi facultas, ut ne titubet ac haereat, quoties ab animo verba diſſentiunt.</hi> Hypocriſie, although it be never ſo cautiouſly acted, will declare it ſelf; and there was never ſuch a happy Eloquence, that did not ſtumble in ſome circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, when words did differ from the habit of the Mind,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſt. p.</hi> 862.</note> as <hi>Quintilian</hi> obſerves; and if perhaps ſome Good Man be deluded by Hypocrites, it may be his goodneſs that has this one bad Conſequence to it; this makes him too credulous, and apt to believe all Men to have the ſame honeſt Intentions with himſelf, and therefore he does not treat them with a due care and circumſpection; however Diſſimulation is no leſs a diſcernable thing to an attentive Obſerver, for all this. Hence therefore the Miniſters of the Goſpel are obliged to be very good Men, if they would rightly perform their great Office, and effectually move the People to the enterpriſe of Vertue and a good Life.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, He that Indulges himſelf in any ſinful Courſes, cannot ſpeak with ſufficient boldneſs. He that has this ſacred imployment upon him, muſt impartially, and with a due ſeverity reprehend Sin, wherever he obſerves it in any Perſon, and as diligently urge to the contrary Vertues; and this is a task that requires ſtrong Courage and Reſolution; for generally Men have too much love to their own Perſons, or to the Animal part of them, which has this influence with it, that it lays a prejudice upon them, and makes them blind towards their own miſcarriages. Some think themſelves unjuſtly cenſured, and that their Life and Manners are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94795:10"/>no matter of reproof, but rather Vertuous and Praiſe-worthy. That which is urged upon them as Profuſeneſs, they eſteem nothing more than an honeſt Liberality, a generous and bountiful temper of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that does much more good in the World, than hoarding up Eſtates by them. He that is taxed with that Idolatrous ſin of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, will not believe it ſo; but rather accounts it a juſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimony, and neceſſary Thriftineſs, if he will provide for his own Family, and that he muſt do, unleſs he will be worſe than an Infidel, and moreover this frugal mode of Living does wholly prevent the ſin of Intemperance, and the manifold Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs and Wickedneſs from it: Thus they will argue, and indeed upon another account, it is not much to be wondered at, that Men are thus miſtaken concerning themſelves, and that they do not know their own Immoralities. For Vice and Vertue touching and bending together in the extream points, 'tis a hard thing critically to define both their Provinces, and ſhew the indiviſible Line of their Separation; as for inſtance, to ſet forth the Confines of Liberality in ſuch a Circumſtance, how far it goes before it degenerate into Profuſeneſs; and upon this account the Miniſters of the Goſpel ought to be Learned Men, and able to determine our Chriſtian Duty in every reſpect of it; but then how angry will ſuch Men be, how full of Stomach and Indignation towards thoſe Charitable Men, that only faſten their deſerved Guilt and Vices upon them? How will they revile them for their juſt Reproof? And whilſt they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging the greateſt Office of Kindneſs to them, <hi>viz.</hi> Reclaiming them from the Error of their ways, they will only repreſent them in the ſtile of Slanderers, and falſe Accuſers of the Brethren, <hi>becauſe</hi> they have no due ſenſe, or a ſelfiſh Opinion of their own Practices.</p>
            <p>But there is a worſe ſort of men to deal with than theſe, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuch as having contracted long Habits of their Vices, have now no due reſentment of them, not ſo much from ignorance at the beginning, as the inſenſibility of Cuſtom in them. How will theſe upon any Chriſtian advice to them, as we have ordinary experience in the Caſe, aſperſe the Prieſthood, and make them the Subjects of their Drollery, becauſe they repreſent their Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94795:10"/>to them with their due Conſequents, and ſo hinder their greater ſatisfaction in them, which through the hardneſs of their Hearts, they could more obtain without this External Suggeſtion, and reminding of them; nay, if they proceed not farther than bare words againſt them, 'tis not that they want any degree of Malice, and Hatred to that purpoſe, but becauſe the Providence of God, either immediately, or in the proviſion of Human Laws, does reſtrain them. How many have ſuffered in this neceſſary part of Charity, for reprehending their Brethren, and endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their amendment? Almoſt all the Old Prophets are inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in this kind, and to whom may be added, a numerous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Chriſtian Martyrs, with him alſo who was in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of theſe two States <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt. So that the Miniſters of the Goſpel, may fitly be repreſented under that ſimile which the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was (Chap. 1.18.) <hi>That God has made them a defenſed City, and an Iron Pillar, and Brazen Walls againſt the whole Land, againſt the Princes thereof, and againſt the People there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi> And be ſure, the greateſt part of theſe being Vicious, will oppoſe and fight with him; now what a mighty Courage muſt he be indued with, what a Divine Valour, and an undaunted Soul muſt he have, as a prerequiſite of <hi>Grace</hi> in him, <hi>which</hi> indeed will make him a defenſed City, who is to maintain himſelf againſt all this reſiſtance. He muſt be arrived at that exalted Pitch, as to be above the Impreſſions of Fear or Favour, before he can enter upon that violent thing <hi>to tell Judah of her Sins, and Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el of her Tranſgreſſions,</hi> who have no mind to hear of them. He muſt be ſuch a Perſon, that will not ſtart back, or deſiſt from this moſt Signal Charity to the Souls of men; for any Injuries of his own, though never ſo many be heaped upon him. If his eyes were opened, and he ſhould ſee whole Legions of Devils march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt him (which indeed they always do, eſpecially in this Buſineſs of Converſion, or reſcue of Souls from them,) he muſt then be reſolved to ſtand his Ground, according to that of the Apoſtle, and in a certain Faith of the event of it, <hi>reſiſt the Devil and he will flee from you:</hi> Nay, if he ſhould ſee Preſent Death advancing towards him, which is more ſenſible to Human
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94795:11"/>Nature, than thoſe inviſible Forces; or, which is worſe, a ſtate of Martyrdom, or long ſufferings, he muſt determine himſelf not to ſhrink at all this, but conſtantly reprove Vice, although that be the Occaſion of all his Miſeries. He muſt neither ſuffer his own Modeſty, which is often the Cauſe of two much Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, nor any apprehenſion from it to deterr, or hinder him in a Prudent Freedom of this Duty. And the reaſon is plain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe otherwiſe he brings the Guilt and Puniſhment of the People upon himſelf: His Office conſiſts in this Charitable thing of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, and he muſt perform it for his own ſecurity, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> (33.7, 8, 9. <hi>Son of man I have ſet thee a Watchman unto the Houſe of Iſrael, therefore thou ſhalt hear the Word at my Mouth, and warn them from me. When I ſay unto the Wicked, O Wicked Man thou ſhalt ſurely dye, if thou doſt not ſpeak to warn the Wicked from his way, that Wicked man ſhall dye in his Iniquity, but his Blood will I require at thine hand. Nevertheleſs, if thou warn the Wicked of his Way, to turn from it, if he do not turn from his Way, he ſhall dye in his Iniquity, but thou haſt delivered thy Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This therefore he muſt do for ſelf-preſervation, in that true reſpect of his own Soul. And now, who is ſufficient for theſe things? Indeed none elſe but the Good Man. He has the courage of Vertue in him, and the Divine Aſſiſtance that belongs to it, and the Bleſſed hopes and expectations of it, and therefore he has no ſuch apprehenſion of theſe outward Sufferings, nor would he ſave the Greateſt Danger in the neglect of one inſtance of doing good, indeed if he ſhould, he would be a loſer by it. This was that Gallant Spirit that reſted upon the Prophets, and firſt Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the Goſpel; Theſe good men were as bold as <hi>Lions,</hi> and were not aſſrighted at any Terrour. What a daring reply was that of <hi>Elijah,</hi> when <hi>Ahab</hi> demanded. <hi>Haſt thou found me, O mine Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my? Yes,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I have found thee, becauſe thou haſt ſold thy ſelf to work evil in the ſight of the Lord,</hi> (1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.20.) And how boldly doth St. <hi>Paul</hi> reaſon of Righteouſneſs, Temperance, and Judgment to come, before <hi>Felix,</hi> who was guilty of both the contrary Vices, which muſt needs make a Judgment a more ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94795:11"/>thing to him, (<hi>Acts</hi> 24.) But why ſhould I recount any more of theſe <hi>Heroes?</hi> Did they not all ſpeak the ſame things? Were they not all inſpired with the ſame Confidence? This is the Noble Temper, and Reſolution of Vertue, which theſe Holy Men had ſuch an exceeding ſhare of. But Vice is a Poor-ſpirited and Baſe thing, it dares not engage with any Difficulties; but bluſhes and ſhrinks back at the leaſt Oppoſition. The Senſe of Guiltineſs going along with it, does utterly debaſe the Mind, or Subject where it is, and makes it unfit for any Generous En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe. If a Wicked man preſumes at any time to reprehend a Vice, perhaps he himſelf is Guilty in the ſame kind, and then what a Sneaking Spirit does appear in him? how does he betray his Boſom-Iniquities, at the naming of them in another? Or if haply he be not Guilty of the ſame things, yet his Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of another kind will check that gallant Courage and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which is requiſite upon ſuch Occaſions, and hinder all the Eſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of his Reproof. A bad Man dares not look a Danger in the Face, nor venture himſelf upon any good Deſign. And indeed no wonder that he is ſo Baſely Timerous, for he wants theſe two great Bottoms of Manly Reſolution, <hi>viz.</hi> a right Conſcience with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him, and the reaſonable Hopes of a better World: his own Mind ſuggeſts to him his after-Miſeries, and therefore he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to make as much of a ſhort Life as he can, and never expoſe it upon any account whatſoever, although it be in the Cauſe of Vertue, that has ſuch an advantage and recompence in it to a Good Man: And therefore how unfit is he for the Sacred Miniſtry, which requires ſo much Confidence in the Diſcharge of it? and how only qualified is the Good Man, who has all Fears removed from him, and therefore can freely rebuke Vice, and uſe a due boldneſs upon all occaſions for it?</p>
            <p n="5">5ly. He that gives himſelf the Liberty of any open Vice, cannot ſpeak with ſufficient Authority; his Doctrines will not be received with that proper Regard and Eſteem that belongs to them. The Miniſter of the Goſpel muſt be a Grave and Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Perſon, ſuch an one as can command Reſpect whereſoever he appears, and create a kind of Reverence for himſelf among
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94795:12"/>all thoſe that Converſe with him, which will alſo give a Credit to his Doctrines. For it is not only ſtrength of Argument that founds a Belief of any thing (as I proved before); but the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Perſon, and his Authority, does often create a more certain Perſwaſion in the Minds of Men. This was the reaſon of the <hi>Ipſe dixit</hi> in the Scholars of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> who yet were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sagacious Perſons, and had the better Judgment of Good Morals in them, they were carried into an limplicit Faith of things, from their great eſteem of their Maſter, that his larger Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, being attended with Integrity of Life, would by no means Impoſe upon them. And indeed theſe two Qualifications, a larger Knowledge, and Integrity of Life, with a due Gravity of Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, muſt needs be very Prevalent upon all thoſe that know, and are acquainted with them. Whatſoever ſuch a Perſon ſays, will be entertained with a kind of Reverence. His Precepts and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, whether he diſſuade from Sin, or exhort to Vertue, will be very Effectual for that purpoſe, and carry ſomething of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion along with them; they will not be able to reſiſt the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Authority by which he ſpeaketh: And his Diſcourſes will not only be a ſtrong diſſuaſive from Sin, but his very ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Perſon will have the ſame effect in it, none daring to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any Undecent thing, while they are in his Converſe, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected by him; nay, his Influence will be as it were Omnipreſent in the ſeveral parts of his Sphere, ſo that Men will be afraid to tranſgreſs in any manner, if it be only probable to come to his Knowledge. Such an Authentick Perſon muſt the Miniſter be, ſuch an Univerſal Reſtraint to all Impiety, in the Place of his Miniſtry. And who is able for this, but only the Vertuous and Good Man, he whoſe Pious Converſation hath got him a Venerable reſpect from all Men, ſo that his words are Powerful upon his Hearers, and always enforces both a ready Aſſent and Conformity to them? If he reprove them for any known Sin, or tell them of ſome unknown Part or Circumſtance of their Duty, they are even compelled by his awfull Authority, and cannot reſiſt or-disbelieve him. Shame it ſelf works them into Compliance, having no Evil Thing to ſay of him. That he hath
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94795:12"/>ſpoken it, who has the undeniable credibility of an exemplary Life, is a ſufficient Demonſtration of it. But a Vicious Perſon can have no ſuch Command or Prevalency upon his Hearers, except it be to the depraving of them. For certainly Sin has a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage from ſuch a Man; if perchance he gives them ſome ſober Inſtruction, they'l preſently entertain him with that common Deriſion, <hi>Phyſitian heal thy ſelf,</hi> give a Proof of thy Skill and Sincerity in thy own Cure, or in the Remedy of thy own Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, before thou preſcribe to other People. And indeed he muſt needs be as Ridiculous as Ineffectuall, that puts on a Big Gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards others, and reproves their Faults with an Authentick Forehead, when he himſelf is guilty in the ſame, or in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind. And therefore, upon this Account alſo, it mightily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Miniſters of the Goſpel to be very Spotleſs Men, that according to the Apoſtle <hi>(Titus</hi> 2.15.) they may rebuke with all Authority, and have a more forcing and irreſiſtible Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon their Charge.</p>
            <p n="6">6ly. A Vicious man cannot be Induſtrious enough in his High Calling, or that great Concern of Saving Souls; he will want a due Vigour and Incitement for it. It is no lazy Imployment, that of the Miniſtry, but which requires an Intenſe Carefulneſs, and Indefatigable Diligence to the right management of it. The Province of him that is called to this Office, is large and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult. <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, when he was upon this Contemplation, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6.) Indeed none is in his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Endowments, although never ſo propitiouſly furniſhed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſpecial Communication and Concourſe with him. For if in every Common Chriſtian, their whole Capacity of a good Life, and true knowledge of the Goſpel, or the Myſteries of God, is from Grace; then the High Station of a Miniſter muſt needs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon this ſame Principle, and in a due performance require an extraordinary Influence of it. And I dare ſay, which may be a common Obſervation, That an Honeſt Mind and Induſtry is more able and more ſucceſsful in the diſcharge of this Office, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in this means Men have a ſpecial Aſſiſtance with them, than the greateſt Natural Parts and quickneſs can promiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94795:13"/>in their own confidence, as they ſtand upon an immodeſt O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of themſelves, and are ſeparate from that Humane means of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, and that bleſſed Conſequence and ſupply of Grace to it.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, He muſt <hi>conſtantly Preach the Word, Reprove, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke, Exhort with all long Suffering, and Doctrine,</hi> (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.) he muſt be very diligent in this particular of his Vocation, always perform it in its due frequency, and never neglect the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn opportunites of it, leſt through any careleſs intermiſſion of his, ſome Soul ſhould periſh for want of timely Advice and Counſel, and then we all know at whoſe hand his blood ſhall be required.</p>
            <p>And in this diſcharge he muſt remember, that Preaching the Goſpel is a very grave and ſerious thing, according to the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Truths therein delivered, and the relation they have to our immortal Souls, or the eternal welfare of them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he muſt not intermingle thoſe improper things of Jeſt, or Ridicule in it, which only puts mens minds into a looſe habit, and ſo hinders all the efficacy of that ſolemn Imployment he is then about.</p>
            <p>And beſides, he muſt beſtow a due Care and Labour in it, that his Diſcourſes in Gods Embaſſie be not Rude and Slovenly, that can only prevail upon ſilly Women laden with ſin; ſuch as are thoſe of our Diſſenting Brethren, and ſuch as the effect of theirs is; but that they may approve themſelves to the Judgments of Men, and convince a larger Capacity, which being determined to an ill Life, can offer ſome more than ordinary defence for it. The Miniſter expoſes God's Cauſe in a careleſs Reprehenſion of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sin, and only confirms a more Sagacious Practitioner in it; when he offers no probable. Diſcourſe, or Inducement againſt it; and Vertue has a great diſadvantage by him, when he does not du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet off the Divine Nature and Beauty of it; and therefore we muſt not make this Great thing of Preaching the Goſpel an Extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pory buſineſs, left we do God and Religion diſſervice in it, and only obtain upon ſimple People; as the Heathens ſaid of old, when the more capable ſort of them, or the more ingenuous Sinners are rather hardened in their Vices, and farther removed, from their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94795:13"/>Repentance, by that very means of it, when it is performed in ſuch a negligent manner; will they not too properly call it, <hi>The fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Preaching?</hi> And ſhall not we change that Calumny of the Apoſtle from the conceited <hi>Corinthians,</hi> into an undeniable Truth concerning our ſelves? It is impoſſible that <hi>Extempory talk,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the nature of Humane Reaſon, that it being ſuch a narrow and confined thing, always proceeds in a Progreſſive manner, and deduces one thing from another; it is impoſſible that <hi>this</hi> ſhould have that Strength and Perſpicuity in it, which Meditation, and a mature ranking of our Thoughts, may well afford in any matter.</p>
            <p>Nor in this lazy deportment can we expect any Inſpiration for our aſſiſtance, whiles we are wanting to our own Faculties, or to what we have in our own Power, and can perform from our ſelves. A due Exertion of our ſelves is always requiſite for the Supplies of Heaven, becauſe it is only a Concourſe which we can reaſonably expect thence, and no <hi>entire Action, which</hi> would deprive us of the eſſential Freedom of our Nature, or of our Nature it ſelf, and turn us into meer Animals, that have a neceſſary Impulſe upon them, and are only acted from an External Principle to them. Indeed the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles did contribute their whole Talent, who having no attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Arts or Sciences, when they were <hi>called to the propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpel,</hi> did readily comply to it, (a ready compliance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that they were capable of,) and therefore, becauſe they did thus contribute their whole Talent, or all that they had in their own Power, they were abundantly ſupplied from Heaven, and particularly choſen for that Office, to which the Gift of Inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was neceſſary at that time; but thoſe that are ſupine and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in this Apoſtolick Function, have no ſuch Plea for it; and if any one ſhould tell me, in whom I ſhould ſee no concurrence of his own Induſtry, that he were inabled to ſpeak from the Spirit, I ſhould only reply, That he was an impudent Impoſtor for that Aſſertion; or, at the beſt, that he were under a high Poſſeſſion of Phrenzy and Melancholly, which he did not rightly diſtinguiſh in him. Indeed this muſt be acknowledged, to the Glory of God, that there is a ſpecial Aſſiſtance in the Office of the Miniſtry; but then this is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways conferred upon our own Labours in it, or when we offer all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94795:14"/>that we are able from our ſelves. But as to that degree or kind of Inſpiration which was upon the Apoſtles, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the Church for ſome
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Till</hi> Conſtantine<hi>'s time, Euſeb. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 32.</note> Centuries, when in that prevalency of <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> and Perſecution from <hi>it,</hi> they had no opportunity of Humane Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; we who live in the peace of the Goſpel, and have all the advantantages to ſtudy and underſtand the Chriſtian Doctrine, in the due uſe of our own <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and common Grace with <hi>that,</hi> we have no need of it, nor can it be expected by us. And this we may take notice of, that what we acquire in a well-deduced Inference from Reaſon, is equally true, and as uſeful, as that which is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturally revealed to us. For our Conviction of the Truth of any thing is only this, That it be clear and evident to our Faculties, which may be in an acquired Propoſition, as well as an inſpired one; and therefore that Knowledge of the Goſpel-doctrines, which we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to in the Humane means of our Studies, with the common Influence of Gods Spirit, is as certain and unqueſtionable, as that which is the ſole Impreſſion of Infinite Wiſdom, and wholly diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Heaven upon us. Now then, there being no extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Effuſions upon Preachers in our days, nor any juſtifiable occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for it, ſuch as might engage God to ſuch an Inſtance; but his Holy Spirit only aſſiſting their honeſt Endeavours, in leſs or larger meaſures, as he pleaſes, what Intenſe Thinking, and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is requiſite on our part, that we may ſpeak the <hi>Tremenda Dei,</hi> the Oracles of God, as we ought to do, and not reflect Incohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Nonſenſe upon him, in <hi>the neglect of our own Faculties,</hi> and want of Heavenly aſſiſtance becauſe of <hi>that,</hi> and ſo preclude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good effect of our Preaching, nay, promote a very ill one from it, that Men deſpiſe this Holy Ordinance, and in ſome proceſs Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion it ſelf, through the rude diſcharge of it? And therefore Preaching being now in a more Humane manner, and upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count a more laborious thing, the People are in a great miſtake, who expect ſuch frequent returns of it, and from this Notion, that 'tis ſuch an eaſie buſineſs, make ſo little recompence for it. And perhaps, which is the Opinion of Great Men, and as able and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert in Preaching as any, one Sermon in a Week, ſuppoſe there
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94795:14"/>ſhould be nothing elſe to divide his time with, that thing is indeed a ſufficient Task for one Man, to be performed with thoſe due thoughts and gravity that belongs to it. Which the more Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians were very ſenſible of, and therefore they had ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Miniſters, or ſeveral Orders of them, in one Church, for the more juſt performance of Gods Service, as Prieſts, and Deacons, and Sub-Deacons, and Readers (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) every one for their proper <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</hi> And although there were <hi>two</hi> appropriate to the Prieſts, Preaching the Words, and Adminiſtring the Sacraments; yet they were diſtinctly managed by them; and thoſe that miniſtred in the Sacraments, which indeed is the moſt Prieſtly thing in that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, had no concern in the other. So far are they miſtaken who make Preaching an eſſential part of the Prieſt-hood. But this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, as many other Errors do, from their want of Knowledge in the Records of the Church; and thoſe who Preached and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed the People, or who laboured in the Word and Doctrine, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, 1 (<hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17.) they had this ſole Province upon them, which ſeems to be the Precept of this ſame Apoſtle, in another place, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 12.7, 8.) He that hath the <hi>gift of Miniſtry, let him wait on his Miniſtry; or he that teacheth, on teaching; or he that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orteth, on exhortation.</hi> But the fervour of Religion in general, as well as Charity, is much abated in our days, and there is no greater Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of this thing, than he indifferency of Men to the due performance of Gods Publick Worſhip, when they do not only not provide for the juſt Miniſtry of his Altar by Many, without which it cannot properly be done, but often not maintain One com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petently, even depriving him of his <hi>equitable</hi> Rights and Suſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, according to the Apoſtle, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.11, 13, 14.). <hi>If we have ſown unto you ſpiritual things, is it a great thing if we ſhall reap your Carnal things? Do ye not know that they which miniſter about holy things, live of the things of the temple? And they which wait at the altar, are partakers with the altar? Even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they which Preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> And now from hence to repreſent Mens Iniquity to them, what a ſmall Compenſation do they commonly make for the whole Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Preacher, that being now in a more induſtrious way, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94795:15"/>the whole Complicated Buſineſs of Holy Orders that they require of him) nay, for the Fruits of his Study, or the whole Imployment of his Life before that, leſs than they would do to a Journyman in ſome honeſt Trade; there are are not many, when 'tis a Voluntary thing, but would give more for three Words of a Lawyer, than for the Miniſtry of an whole year. This argues the little Senſe of Religion that Men commonly have, or the ſmall regard to their Souls, and that their Great Concerns are all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted about their Bodies: But I could wiſh, there were a certain Settlement in all Places, according to Gods own Appointment among the Jews; I could wiſh this, for the Freedom of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and the Common advantage in that thing, that thoſe of the Prieſtly Function might not be tempted only to Propheſie ſmooth things, and to humour the People in, their Vices, becauſe of their dependance upon them; or indeed to ſell them to Schiſm and Rebellion, <hi>for pieces of Bread and handfuls of Barley,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks, (<hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.19.) Which I wiſh we had not too much experienced in our days, and, in a timely Prevention of the Government, may never experience afterwards.</p>
            <p>And then as to the extent of Preaching; he that maintains this Office, muſt not only direct his Diſcourſes Univerſally againſt Sin, but againſt all the ſeveral ſorts and kinds of it, there ſcarce being any which may not juſtly be expected to reign in ſome Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual of a Common Aſſembly; I ſay, he muſt be ſo particular, leſt he ſhould ſuffer ſome Soul ſecurely and ignorantly, or in the Security that Ignorance always contains in it, to run on into its own Ruine. For although the Mind of Man be at firſt through the Goodneſs of his Maker, a very tender and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing, yet in any ones indulging of himſelf in Sin, and in the Influence of that, it may be hardned, and have a certain inſenſibility, which is Ignorance, and no due apprehenſion of things brought into it; and this the Miniſter muſt endeavour to ſoften and reſtore, in ſuitable Diſcourſes, or Applications to it. And this Univerſal reprehenſion of Sin, muſt needs be a very la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious Task, ſeeing that Vice, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> well obſerves, is ſo large and manifold (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Eth. p.</hi> 29.) Vertue, which ought
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94795:15"/>to be the ſcope and meaſure of all our Actions, although it have ſome Latitude or Degrees in it, is but one ſimple thing; but there are infinite Ways; to digreſs from it: And he muſt not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give a particular Scheme of all Sins, but likewiſe repreſent their proper Aggravations, with thoſe diſmal Conſequences that do attend the continuance in them, and then add his Diſuaſives from them, and theſe not only thoſe General ones from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude of Sin againſt our Maker, and againſt our Redeemer, who Created us after his own Image, and who reſtored us to that again, in his Sufferings for us; nor from the conſideration of the great Debaſement that Sin brings into our Nature, with the like; but he muſt apply proper Remedies for every ſeveral Vice, or Diſtemper of the Soul, ſuch as may have a ſingular reſpect in them.</p>
            <p>And then there is a great Diſcretion to be uſed in his Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. There are different ſorts of Men to be dealt withal, and thoſe labouring under different Maladies, and Affections of the Mind; ſo that he muſt take a ſpecial heed to his Doctrine, if he preach up the Allowances of the Goſpel, that that does not require a perfect unſinning Obedience, but admits of Sins of Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and ſudden ſurreption, which may be called Sins of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, when we have not a due ſpace to reflect upon them; that it admits of theſe, even when we are within the Covenant of Grace, and Partakers of the Heavenly Promiſes, if putting them into our Daily Confeſſions, we beg Pardon for them, and uſe our honeſt Endeavours againſt them for the time to come. Yet this Doctrine, although very neceſſary for the weaker Brethren, to maintain a right Faith in them, or to preſerve them from Deſpair; yet bolder Spirited Chriſtians, that think too well of themſelves, and from that Selfiſh reſpect or Opinion, do not ſufficiently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between Wilfull Sins, and thoſe of Humane Infirmity, will grow preſumptious upon it, and caſt off that conſtant Care, and Diligence that is neceſſary in a Chriſtian Life, or that they ought to maintain in all their Actions; on the contrary, if he too frequently inſiſt upon the Black demerit of Sin, how every Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, or every ſingle Pollution thereof, unleſs waſhed away
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94795:16"/>by a ſincere Repentance in the Blood of our Saviour, does deſerve Eternal Death, or Miſery in the other World, which are Truths great, and certain, and very uſeful to beat down the ſwelling Pride and Arrogance of ſome Men; yet others being conſcious to themſelves of their frequent Miſcarriages, and imputing too little to <hi>Humane Imbecillity, or the inherent appetites of a ſenſual Nature,</hi> will be apt to fall into deſpair from this Doctrine, and becauſe they cannot attain to an abſolute Righteouſneſs, perhaps they'll endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour after none at all, becoming careleſs and ſtupid in the work of their Salvation, or quite deſiſting from any attempts of it, in a kind of diffidence of Gods Mercy, and too aggravated apprehenſions of their own Sins. And therefore he muſt in great Prudence apply to Men who have theſe different diſpoſitions in them, and ſo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per his Diſcourſes with Law and Goſpel, that he may promote a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral benefit, or advance a juſt Confidence, and hinder Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in all of them.</p>
            <p>And perhaps he muſt not inſiſt upon meer Terror to the moſt obſtinate Sinner, leſt poſſibly, if they have any Intervals of Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from the importunity of their Vices, they ſhould be ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up of too much Sorrow, or fall into Diſpair by that means; but he muſt always intermingle, or jointly apply the Conſolations of the Goſpel, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> adviſes in the inſtance of the <hi>moſt abominable Offender,</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7, 8) that ſo they may have a due encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Repentance and a good Life; eſpecially if he obſerve a tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly humble and contrite Spirit in them, which is the proper qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation for Mercy. Leſt therefore this effect of too much Sorrow ſhould follow from a Diſcourſe of Mens Terrours, in a more likely Diſpoſition for it, he muſt in the Language of the Prophet, and in the Office of Chriſt, whoſe Miniſter he is, <hi>(Iſa.</hi> 61.3.) <hi>appoint unto them that mourn in Sion beauty for aſhes, the oyl of joy for mourning, the garment of praiſe for the ſpirit of heavineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then, whether in Preaching, or private Conference, he moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially endeavour imploying a main part of his Care and Diligence in that thing, to convince the Gainſayers, or bring back thoſe that are departed from us, he muſt not ſatisfie himſelf with their known ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy, that they are almoſt irreclaimable becauſe of that, but
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94795:16"/>he muſt try all Experiments, uſe his utmoſt Contrivance, in a due Charity towards them, to recover thoſe Souls for whom Chriſt died, and enſtate them in the <hi>ordinary method of Salvation;</hi> and therefore it is very proper to repreſent the danger of Schiſm, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of Communion of the <hi>Church: This</hi> is the Myſtical Body or Corporation of Chriſt, in which are the more liberal influences of God's Spirit, and the free Circulation of all Heavenly Graces, as the Apoſtle illuſtrates by the ſimilitude of the Head and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the Natural Body, (<hi>Eph.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.19.) And therefore thoſe that divide from the Church, or cut themſelves off from Communion with it, they have not that ſpecial relation of Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to Chriſt, and ſo cannot enjoy ſuch a free intercourſe of Grace from him, or any certain hopes of Eternal Happineſs in his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation for Mankind, both which are diſpenſed conſequentially to one another, in this relation of Memberſhip to him. All that can be ſaid for ſuch Perſons is, That they having voluntarily caſt themſelves out of thoſe means of Salvation which God has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, are left to his extraordinary Mercy, in a much worſe caſe than many of the Heathens, or in a great abatement of their hopes, who perhaps never had the opportunity of joyning themſelves to, the Church of God, and maintaining one Uniform Worſhip with it.</p>
            <p>And now, if poſſibly theſe Men ſhould affirm themſelves to be the true Church, and ſo think to remove this Conſequence from them, it is very demonſtrable, that our Church is not only the moſt reaſonable Inſtitution of a Church, which may be even defended in a rational way, without the advantage of Antiquity, but the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ectype from the Apoſtles, or the neareſt reſemblance of their Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, and the moſt Apoſtolick in the World, which none can deny without betraying a lamentable defect in Primitive Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>And if they ſhould ſtill defend themſelves, that their Differences to us does not amount to a Diſ-union from us, or from our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Church, but that notwithſtanding they may be ſtill account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Fellowſhip with it; it is too apparent, that <hi>thoſe who</hi> do not conſent in that particular Order, Government, and Miniſtry which God has ordained in his Church, but innovate in ſome of theſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94795:17"/>reſpects; that is, <hi>who</hi> either will not Conform with an Epiſcopal Church, or Chriſtian Society, governed in the moſt Primitive manner by Biſhops, whom St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſo often ſtyles the Principles of Unity, or that which makes a Church, when it is conjoyned to one Biſhop, as the viſible Head of it: And therefore the <hi>Nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, Donatiſts, Meletians,</hi> who maintained another Head of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, namely, the Martyrs, were all accounted Schiſmaticks by him, and other Fathers; or <hi>thoſe who</hi> will not ſubmit to the Primitive Diſcipline of the <hi>Church, which was ſetled and inſtituted by the Apoſtles,</hi> they may well be ſaid to renounce, and recede from <hi>their</hi> Church, becauſe in this Obſtinacy, or incomplyance they promote Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Diſcord in the Church, and ſo violating that indiſpenſible Charity which ought to be in it, they loſe their Chriſtian Rights, or ceaſe to be of it. Eſpecially thoſe that will not Communicate in the Sacraments of the Church, theſe being the eſſential Bonds of of its Communion, they muſt needs be accounted as divided Branches, and not of that Society; indeed they have no publick badge to maintain themſelves Chriſtians from, and if they triumph in a good Life, as many of them do, they may rather be reckoned for a ſort of Moral Religioniſts, then ſuch as can pretend to Chriſts Name, or the Religion that he founded.</p>
            <p>And now after all this, if we conſider the Apoſtles account of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> which more plainly expreſſes the danger thereof, ſeeing <hi>it</hi> has the ſame relation to our Church, or ours being ſpecifically the ſame with that which he ſounded, it may be more affecting, and more inforce a Reformation; (<hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19.) where he reckons up <hi>Strife, Seditions, Hereſies,</hi> with thoſe other abominable works of the Fleſh, that does exclude from the Kingdom of God; and then he ſhews the particular Character of this Sin, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3.) <hi>Whereas there is among you envying, and ſtrife, and diviſions, are ye not carnal, and walk as men?</hi> And St. <hi>Jude</hi> ſaith the ſame thing, that <hi>thoſe who ſeparate themſelves are ſenſual, having not the Spirit; (verſ.</hi> 19.) and to ſpeak plainly, 'tis evident, that either Pride, which has always Obſtinacy a Concomitant of it, that they would be accounted gifted Men, and have the credit of a <hi>ſpecial acquaintance</hi> with the Spirit, <hi>which</hi> they think cannot conſiſt with
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94795:17"/>a ſet Liturgy, although never ſo well compoſed, both as to the extent of Prayer, or good things that we ſhould requeſt for, and proper expreſſions of Devotion to promote a due Affection in us: it is this <hi>ſame Pride or Covetouſneſs, and ſome ſecular advantages from it,</hi> that affords the reaſon of all Diſſenters, <hi>which</hi> indeed are as carnal things, as Intemperance, or any other bodily enormity can be.</p>
            <p>There can be no Plea of Conſcience for it, at leaſt in the more knowing of them; and when they urge this, they either in their proper art of diſſimulation ſpeak againſt their own Conſcience, and true Notions of things, and ſo deceive ſome other honeſt People; or they have contracted an habitual prejudice from one of theſe two Vices, and their Indulgence in them, and ſo are under a Self-delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or deceive themſelves in the caſe. And I am confident that if our Non-conforming Brethren ſhould honeſtly examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their own minds, they would find, where profit does not determine, a great Preference of themſelves, and mean Opinion of other Chriſtians, who live in the ſober uſe of their own Faculties, and the common means of Grace, without any pretentions to Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, or the extraordinary gifts of Gods Spirit; I ſay, they would find this Spiritual Pride in them, which indeed makes them what they are, or Diſſenters from us; as alſo, hinders them from a due Confeſſion of their Sin, and returning to us. This, I am confident, is the predominant Principle in all thoſe that ſeparate from us, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they began their Separation, whether from themſelves, or had it more excuſably derived to them through Education; yet this is in them, namely, a Self-applauſe, and contempt of others; and indeed the Apoſtle reſolves it into this, (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.2, 3.) as will plainly appear from a due reflection on that place; and therefore I believe, the beſt method with them is, firſt to ſubdue this unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Swelling, or Impoſthume of theirs, to advance ſome So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety in them, and a juſt Opinion of themſelves, which only will make them capable of Conviction, or Reconcilement to the Church. For while they continue in their Pride, they continue in their Prejudice alſo, this being one effect of it, and have no free uſe of their judging Faculties. And therefore this Mountain is firſt to be removed, which indeed is a Moliminous enterpriſe, before we can do any good with them.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:94795:18"/>
            <p>And then he may alſo offer the civil ſin of Separation, or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to Lawful Authority, in dividing from <hi>a National Church,</hi> to <hi>which</hi> Uniformity is abſolutely neceſſary; all difference of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, by ranking Men into ſeveral Parties, and promoting ſeveral Opinions, and Aſſections in them, inevitably making, if not an actual Diſturbance, a moſt certain diſpoſition for it in the State. And this is the Eternal reaſon of Penal Laws in Religion, to ſecure the External Peace of any Kingdom. And therefore the Miniſter muſt inforce the indiſpenſible Obligation that thoſe of any Society, or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment are under, to conform with the publick expreſſion of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or the practice of the Church there; and nothing can juſtifie a Diviſion from it, but only ſinful terms of Communion with it, which I am certain none can charge with any colour of Argument, ſo as to ſatisfie an Impartial Spirit in the thing, upon the moſt Pure and Primitive Church of Chriſt, in reſpect of outward Form and Diſcipline, as we may well maintain ours to be.</p>
            <p>And then he may farther repreſent <hi>the great Bleſſings of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> which in their Separation they deprive themſelves of, <hi>when the Publick Service is an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform thing, and our Prayers are ſent up from an unanimous Conſent, which</hi> gives the greateſt prevalence to them, according to that of the Pſalmiſt, comprehending the true Church of God, whether <hi>Jewiſh</hi> or Chriſtian, (<hi>Pſalm</hi> 133.) <hi>Behold how good and joyful a thing it is for Brethren to dwell together in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.—It is like the dew of</hi> Hermon, <hi>and as the dew that deſcended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Mountains of</hi> Zion; <hi>for there the Lord promiſed his Bleſſing, and Life for evermore.</hi> And moreover, it is not only very decorus, but there ſeems to be a neceſſity for it, that <hi>they</hi> ſhould maintain an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable Peace and Uniformity among themſelves, <hi>who</hi> all pretend to be of <hi>one body</hi> or Chriſtian Community, all lay claim to <hi>one Spirit,</hi> the Eternal Comforter, all <hi>are called into one hope of their calling,</hi> all acknowledge <hi>one Lord,</hi> the Head and Redeemer of his Church <hi>one Faith, one Baptiſm, one God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in as all,</hi> as the Apoſtle argues, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.3.</p>
            <p>And in all this management, I am apt to think, that although Pride and Prejudice, or Intereſt in ſome Perſons, be the whole ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94795:18"/>of Separation, which would almoſt put one out of temper to diſpute with thoſe People; yet a due Candor or Argument, managed in a courteous manner, is the moſt effectual means to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim them, and convince them of their Error, as indeed it is to convince any. Ill Language, or fixing Names upon any Perſon, will never work a Converſion in him, but rather engage him in a bold defence of himſelf, and his Errors, both together, that he may thus remove ſuch an Aſperſion from him; this indeed is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſ-ingenuous; but I believe 'tis Natural to moſt Men; and therefore Railing, whether in the Pulpit, or other places, and Conference with Men, as it is a very Unchriſtian thing, and a great Treſpaſs upon Charity, eſpecially that moſt Charitable Office of Preaching, or Beneficence to Souls; ſo it is a very improper proceeding to convince any, or make them Proſelytes to a good Cauſe; nay, one may eaſily obſerve in a due reflection on Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, that it will rather ſet them at deſiance from it. And therefore thoſe Unchriſtian Preachers, that uſe Railing in their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, beſides a baſe Temper they have antecedently in them, they are rather guilty of fortifying People in their ill Courſes, than doing any Service to their Converſion. And I wonder how they can ſatisfie themſelves in this deportment. There is a duty of Humanity incumbent upon us towards all Men, how Wicked and Perverſe ſoever, and we muſt treat them with the proper reſpect of Humane Creatures, if we ſhould find them no Chriſtians; ſo that this thing of Railing is a caſting off the Manhood it ſelf, with the neceſſary Civility that is in it, and belongs to it, as well as the Candor of the Goſpel, which adds a farther degree to this Civility. And therefore that advice of the Apoſtle, is both upon a Natural account, and a Chriſtian, (<hi>Eph.</hi> 4.31.) <hi>Let all bitterneſs, and wrath, and anger, and clamour, and evil ſpeaking be put away from you, with all malice:</hi> and we read that <hi>Michael,</hi> when <hi>contending with the Devil</hi> himſelf, <hi>he durſt not bring a railing accuſation againſt him,</hi> (Jud. 9.) And the other Angels did behave themſelves in the ſame manner, (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11.) ſo that to <hi>beſtow ill language</hi> upon any, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the inefficacy of it to any good Purpoſe, can never be juſtified in any Perſon; and perhaps <hi>this</hi> being ſo contrary to Charity, the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94795:19"/>great diſtinguiſhing thing of the Goſpel, argues a worſe diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in him that uſes it, than any he can meet with in other Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And therefore fairneſs of Speech, and Argument, is the beſt method, both for our ſelves, and thoſe we converſe with, in order to promote a due advantage to them in our Diſcourſes with them.</p>
            <p>But then a Miniſter in all his Candor of Language with this Party of Men, muſt be ſure to maintain his Ground ſtill, or the Injunctions of the Church, and make no Condeſcentions from them in any thing: indeed in reſpect to a good Conſcience he cannot do it, (and whether it be adviſable in the State, 'tis not for me to determine.) The example of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.20.21.) who was a Jew in ſome inſtances, and Conformable to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Worſhip of the Heathens in others, does not at all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend our Caſe. He might do that, when the Church had not ſet her Authority upon any certain Form of Worſhip, or when the Publick Service was more free, and unſettled, which we cannot do who live under <hi>a legal Eſtabliſhment of Religion;</hi> and a Canonical Obedience to <hi>that.</hi> And I dare ſay that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was as punctual an Obſerver of the Decrees of that firſt Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council held at <hi>Jeruſalem, (Acts.</hi> 15.20.) as any of us can be of thoſe of our own National Church; and therefore when this Method of Gentleneſs will not prevail upon them, then it is neceſſary that he proceed to that extream thing of <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Cenſures, or the Diſcipline of the Church,</hi> as our Saviour lays down, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17.) <hi>which</hi> was the conſtant Practiſe of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and at leaſt approved by God from the cuſtom of the <hi>Jews,</hi> if not poſitively inſtituted by him. And indeed this is the moſt proper Method to reduce and reclaim an Obſtinate Sinner, who moſt likely in a due Puniſhment may have his prejudice much abated, or come to a free conſideration of things, which will certainly produce a Reformation in him; or if this Effect fail upon himſelf, through an inflexible hardneſs, yet his circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance may be very Beneficial to others, to deter them from the like Offences; and if his Guilt be ſo aggravated in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of Civil Commerce, to hinder the Influence of his Vices.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:94795:19"/>And I am Confident that our indulgence to obſtinate Sinners, whether in the Church, or Diſſenters from it, who through their Obſtinacy have almoſt loſt their right to our Chriſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or have no farther Plea for fair means; I am confident that our Indulgence, or neglect of <hi>Cenſures</hi> towards them, <hi>which</hi> are the Weapons of our Warfare in this reſpect, and which makes the Church of God as terrible as an Army with Banners, caſting out every thing that defileth, or worketh Abomination from that Holy Communion; this is the Cauſe of that great Atheiſm and Profaneneſs that is in the Church, and that numerous Separation from it, and we ſhall never deliver our ſelves from theſe two, till we reaſſume this Primitive Diſcipline and only Remedy of them.</p>
            <p>This is the Province of a Preacher, and theſe good things, or theſe Precepts of Holineſs, he muſt inculcate upon his Charge, not after the manner of Men, or with that remiſneſs that is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed in indifferent matters, but with a proper importunity, and earneſt Perſwaſion, ſo as to ſignifie the moment of that concern he is then about, which is no leſs than the Salvation of Souls; one whereof is of more account than many worlds. He muſt, like the Apoſtles, (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20.) reckoning <hi>himſelf the Ambaſſador of Chriſt, beſeech men, in Chriſt's ſtead, to be reconciled unto God;</hi> he muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that he is <hi>Chriſts</hi> Proxy here upon Earth, and therefore he ought to treat with Men after the ſame affectionate manner, that <hi>he</hi> did, calling them to Repentance and Reformation of their Lives, with ſuch a Compaſſion towards them; <hi>that they would abound in all vertue, and continue in the ſame with all patience, and perſeverance unto the end, when they ſhall receive the Crown of righteouſneſs, which Chriſt the righteous judge ſhall give them at that day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he muſt not think that he hath wholly diſcharged himſelf in Preaching, there are ſeveral other things, which from his Office, and ſpecial relation to the Goſpel, are incumbent upon him, He muſt be a Peace-maker as far as he is able,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>This was the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Practice of the Great Dr.</hi> Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon, <hi>in his Life,</hi> p. 13.</note> interpoſe himſelf as a common Arbitrator, and endeavour to make up all the differences of his Charge, preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as much as he can, the uſe of <hi>Law</hi> among them, and thoſe uncharitable affections of Malice
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94795:20"/>and Hatred that proceed from it; which certainly is a great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt the growth and advancement of the peaceful tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Goſpel in the minds of Men, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.7.) <hi>There is utterly a fault among you, becauſe you go to Law one with another: Why do ye not rather take wrong? Why do ye not rather ſuffer your ſelves to be defrauded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was none of this litigious Proceſs among the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, a Friendly reference was the common Deciſion, or an end of all Controverſies with them.</p>
            <p>And then 'tis another important Office of his to viſit the Sick, thoſe that lye upon the Bed of languiſhing, to aſſiſt their Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to afford them his Ghoſtly Counſel, in the <hi>method</hi> of their Repentance, <hi>which</hi> may be moſt proper for them, uſing all poſſible endeavours to deliver a Soul into the hands of Chriſt, and the glorious Armies of the Church triumphant: He muſt, according to the pattern of his great Maſter, continually go about in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince doing good, be a general Superviſor of all their Actions, and reprehend Vice in his Converſation, as well as in the Pulpit; not thinking that his whole office of Reproof, or Inſtruction is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed there. He muſt be a Preacher of Righteouſneſs in all places, and reprove, by the influence of a vertuous Example, where he cannot come in Perſon. All this he muſt do in this great employment of ſaving Souls, which if he perform well, with that ſpecial regard and diligence that he ought to do, let God deal with his People as he pleaſes, as ſhall be moſt agreeable to his infinite Goodneſs and Juſtice, he has delivered his own Soul, and laid up in ſtore for himſelf a good Foundation againſt the time to come; but if he doth not thus diſcharge himſelf, woe unto him, yea, ten thouſand woes, all the Coals and Miſeries of his neglected Charge ſhall be heaped upon him.</p>
            <p>And now who may we ſuppoſe will faithfully perform all this, there muſt certainly be ſome great incitement, ſome prevailing motive or other, in order to it? He muſt be invigorated with a ſtrange Zeal, <hi>which</hi> only will furniſh him with a due patience to that purpoſe: Who can paſs through ſo many difficulties, and ſuſtain ſuch a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince? And nothing can be ſufficient for this, but that prevailing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:94795:20"/>motive above all others, the love of God working in him, and powerfully inciting him to all poſſible inſtances of his Glory. Which love of God muſt needs embrace his whole image in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, and extend it ſelf to all Men in an eminent meaſure. So that he who has the Love of God muſt needs be indued with fervent Charity, and have vehement impulſes in his Spirit, towards the procurement of a common Salvation in the World. Indeed. Love of God, and Charity to Men, are not ſeparable, or cannot be diſtinguiſhed from one another, but are only an extenſion of the ſame thing; this is indiviſible, or theſe two always go toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And therefore St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, (1 <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.20.) <hi>If a man ſay he loveth God and hateth his Brother, he is a Lyer.</hi> If he be poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of this Love, which is always maintained upon a true Faith, and cannot be ſeparate from it, then no difficulties, nor hard adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures whatſoever will terrifie him, when there is hopes of winning a Soul, and enlarging the Borders of Chriſts Kingdom. This was exemplified in St. <hi>Paul;</hi> the love of Chriſt conſtrained him, and the exceeding deſire he had for the Salvation of his Brethren, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from that ſtrange imprecation (<hi>Rom.</hi> 9.3.) when he wiſhed himſelf accurſed from Chriſt for their ſake, that is, to be excluded from the Communion of Chriſts Church, which hath ſuch certain Hopes and Bleſſings in it, and be as a Heathen Man, and a Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, or in the ſtate of the Heathen World, which does ſufficiently denote thoſe accurſed that are ſo, if they were but truly ſenſible of it; and then having this complicated Motive in him, how does he labour to gain Proſelytes in the Chriſtian Faith? <hi>How does he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a ſervant, a labourer with his own hands?</hi> Depriving himſelf of the rewards of the Altar: <hi>A Jew</hi> receding from many Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Chriſtian Liberty; <hi>to thoſe without the law, as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out law, even all things to all men</hi> (as far as the Goſpel diſpenſation, and the more unſettled condition of the Church at that time would allow him) that he might by all means ſave ſome: Neither was his Charity only confined to his Brethren, or Kinſmen, according to the Fleſh, but he travelled over the greateſt part of the habitable World, not to ſee ſeveral Countries, or underſtand diſſerent Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or behold the State and Splendor of Earthly Kingdoms, for his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94795:21"/>Learned Mind was furniſhed with all this before; and having a Soul ſo full of Heaven, where he had once been, he mightily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed the Pomps and Pageantry of this World, which indeed any good Chriſtian would do, eſpecially upon his advantage of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview of them both; but it was ſtill that more generous deſign to ſave Souls, and propagate in all places the Divine Life, and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Goſpel, that gave the Reaſon of his Labours: But Vicious Men, wanting theſe two Motives, or double Principle in their Spirits, <hi>viz.</hi> An ardent Love of <hi>God;</hi> for if they were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of this, they would not continue in any willful Sin, which is Enmity againſt <hi>him;</hi> and alſo, a hearty concern for the Good of Men, the reflex act of the former; I ſay, they wanting this double Principle, which only can excite them to the inceſſant Labours, or painful Imployment of the Miniſtry, and enable them under it, they can never perform it with that due care that is requiſite in it, but will rather be like thoſe watchmen in (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.10.) whom that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet deſcribes, as wanting ſeveral of their Senſes, that they were blind, ignorant, dumb Dogs, who could not bark, or give ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent notice of Sin and Judgment, Sleeping, lying down, loving to ſlumber, which are all to denote a careleſs Paſtor: But let ſuch Shepherds know, that God will certainly be againſt them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire his Flock at their hands.</p>
            <p>But Seventhly, Suppoſing that a Vicious Man could be ſound in his Principles, and induſtrious in his Calling, with the other requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites of a Miniſter, that I have here mentioned, which I believe is morally impoſſible, yet his ill Example will much hinder, if not wholly diſappoint the good effect of his Doctrine. The Examples of Governours, whether tending to Vice or Vertue, have a very large and prevailing Influence. This is a thing of familiar Obſervation, and every Age does abound with freſh inſtances of it; but the worſer Examples, becauſe of the depraved Inclinations of Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which we have either wholly contracted, or much improved upon us; theſe Examples are more ſpreading: Moſt Men are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to gratifie their ſenſual Appetites, and are very glad when they can meet with any ſmall Argument to that purpoſe; but no Examples are of more peſtulential conſequence, than thoſe of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94795:21"/>Clergy: For thoſe things that ſhould aggravate and heighten the ſenſe of their Crimes, create a ſtronger deteſtation of them, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>their Sacred Function, and larger Knowledge of Divine things,</hi> theſe prove great perſwaſives and encouragements to the ſame Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties. For they will ſay, at leaſt the more ignorant ſort of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or the more habitual in their Vices, theſe having more Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding than we have, are alſo obliged to a greater Sanctimony, and ſtrictneſs of living: Why therefore ſhould we deprive our ſelves of thoſe Liberties, and Pleaſures, thoſe neceſſary recompenſes of a careful Life, which they enjoy, eſpecially when 'tis probable that our ſcant knowledge and notion of things does only reſtrain us? For if either of thoſe Actions were ſinful, which we ſuppoſe ſo, or were attended with ſuch diſmal conſequences, then certainly they, whoſe Lips muſt preſerve Knowledge, and who are as nearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the caſe as we are, would perceive it, and live otherwiſe. And thus the more eminent their Station, the more ſolemn their Charge is, the farthey will their ill Example dilate, and carry a more ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Contagion along with it. And hence we read in the Canons of the ancient Church, that <hi>Prieſts</hi> were often depoſed for ſmall Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences; not from this Opinion, that ſuch being ſo indiſpoſed for Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, did fruſtrate the event of them; (for 'twas only one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Sect of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> who maintained the Piety of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, as neceſſary to the efficacy of his Miniſtry, or the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments adminiſtred by him) but eſpecially to prevent the great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency of an ill Example upon thoſe below them, by ſhewing ſome remarkable inſtance upon <hi>them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, to conclude, If the Good Man only be Sound and Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox in his Principles; if he be an Univerſal Teacher, both to diſſuade from Vice in general, and exhort to every particular Vertue; if he be the moſt perſwaſive and prevalent Orator; if he hath that holy boldneſs from his own innocency, to be affrighted with none Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts, or terrors of wicked Men; if he hath a vigorous <hi>love of</hi> God in his Spirit, and <hi>fervent Charity towards</hi> his Brethren, <hi>which is only another branch of it,</hi> ſo that he will refuſe no labours, or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome enterpriſes whatſoever, for the <hi>advancement of Gods Glory, and the Salvation of Souls, which are only two notions ill divided
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:94795:22"/>and the ſame thing;</hi> if he tranſcribe his Doctrines into his own pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and ſhew himſelf a pattern of good Works, and by this means, in a Vertuous Life, has gained a great Veneration among all People, ſo that he carries a kind of Authority along with him, thoſe of the contrary part being aſhamed, having no ill thing to ſay of him: If the Good Man hath all theſe gifts and qualifications in him, then he muſt needs be the moſt ſucceſsful Preacher, and the Goſpel will beſt thrive and proſper under his endeavours: And if a bad Man want all theſe, then he is never like to promote Religion in the World, or bring any advancement to Chriſt's Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And therefore as many of us as have this ſacred Imployment upon us, to be Labourers in Chriſts Vine-yard, <hi>muſt cleanſe our ſelves from all ſilthineſs, both of fleſh and ſpirit, perſecting holineſs in the fear of the Lord.</hi> We muſt be ſpotleſs, and irreproveable, not only for our own ſakes, but for the ſakes of the People among whom we Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe and Live; we ſhould aſcend to ſome eminent degrees of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and Holineſs. Our grent calling requires it from us, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contented with the common meaſures of the World, however we muſt preſerve our ſelves from any thing of Scandal, or open Impieties, leſt we bring a diſparagement to the Goſpel, and hinder the influence of it in the minds of Men, they are in a great miſtake, that think themſelves only fitted for the Miniſtry by their <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which</hi> indifferently is an Inſtrument, either of Good or Evil, according to the hands it happens to fall into. And I dare boldly affirm, That abſtracted Learning, when 'tis ſeparated from Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is the moſt pernicious thing in the Chriſtian World, and has produced the greateſt miſchief in it. How came ſo many Hereſies and <hi>baſe Notions</hi> among us, <hi>which</hi> always have ill Practices found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon them, but only that ſome Vicious Man, through his Parts, and acquired Knowledge, became able to defend his Vices, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend them to the World, under the ſpecious habit and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Vertue? It is extreamly better to want Learning, when it is not directed by Vertue, than to have ſuch an ambiguous thing in us, which may eaſily produce ſuch an ill conſequence of it. And therefore we muſt eſpecially endeavour after a more ſignal Holineſs, as a juſt qualification for the Miniſtry, which is alſo the beſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:94795:22"/>of attaining to true Learning. Others may ſpend their time in trifling Notions, and pretend to an Univerſal acquaintance with all Nature, as if they had been at Counſel with the Almighty when he made the World; yet if they'll deal but ingenuouſly with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they muſt ſtill confeſs that there are abundance of occult qualities, even in the moſt ordinary things, and that they cannot preſume to the true Philoſophy of one Single graſs-pile; but the Good Man is the only Scholar, his Learning is in a better kind, and of a more uſeful conſequence, both to himſelf and the whole World; for he hath Gods Bleſſing in all his Studies, and is directed and aſſiſted by it. If then we would not only fit our ſelves for the more ſacred Character of the Clergy, but alſo be good Proficients in true Learning, we muſt begin at Vertue, and found all our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours upon it, or manage them all in a joynt exerciſe of it, and then we ſhall attain to the moſt concerning Knowledge, or the beſt Improvements that we are capable of, (which others can never do in all their unſanctified Labours) according to that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>The Fear of the Lord is the beginning of wiſdom, a good underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing have all they that do thereafter.</hi> And if we do not then ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutely know the ſeveral motions and deſignments of Nature, in her ſmalleſt Operations, which ſome fondly pretend to, the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier we, this argues that we are better imployed, and that our more uſeful Contemplations are not interrupted with inſignificant and <hi>empty ſubtilties, ſuch</hi> as have no influence upon the Mind, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards any Moral improvement of it. That we may all of us pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in this method to improve our ſelves, and ſerve God in his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church, God of his Infinite Mercy grant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
